Guide to the Edwin Rogers Embree Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edwin Rogers Embree papers
1903-1956
MS 198
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.5
(9 boxes)
The papers consist of personal and professional correspondence; family journals (1918-1949) of trips to Europe, China, Samoa, Java and Central America; and articles, book reviews and speeches on cultural anthropology (particularly on the Pacific), education, medicine, American race relations, and philanthropic institutions. Among Embree's professional papers are also financial statements and other materials relating to the Julius Rosenwald Fund, the Rockefeller Foundation and other philanthropies with which he was associated. Prominent correspondents include James Bryant Conant, Clarence Day, Harold Ickes, Esther Rauschenbush, Walter Reuther, John D. Rockefeller and Harold Taylor.
Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers), 1883-1950
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Catherine Embree Harris, 1964, 1967.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection also available on microfilm (7,915 frames on 9 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM167.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Correspondence. II. Family Journals. III. Articles, Speeches, and Talks. IV. Books. V. Miscellaneous.
Scope and Contents
The Edwin Rogers Embree Papers consist of approximately 3,000 items, filed in nine archive boxes. The collection contains personal and professional correspondence (especially with Clarence Day), as well as correspondence concerning several of Embree's books. Also included in the collection are the journals of his trips abroad and articles, book reviews, and speeches on cultural anthropology, education, medicine, nursing, race relations, and religion. These materials have been arranged into the following five series.
SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or subject and chronologically within the files; a chronological file of general correspondence precedes the alphabetical listing. Of particular note is the rather extensive correspondence with Clarence Day between 1926 and 1936. It should also be noted that correspondence exists within other series in this collection, especially where it concerns articles or books that Mr. Embree wrote.
SERIES II. FAMILY JOURNALS contains the journals that Edwin Embree kept on his travels around the world. The journals (1918-1949) covering travel in all major areas of the world, was usually mimeographed and sent to friends and family. For additional accounts of these trips see the journals of Edwin's son, John Fee Embree. (Historical Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University).
SERIES III. ARTICLES, SPEECHES, AND TALKS is arranged alphabetically by general subject and chronologically within the subject files. Included is some correspondence regarding various speeches and articles by Embree, especially the article "Timid Billions" which appeared in the March, 1949, issue of Harpers and reflected on Embree's many years working with philanthropic foundations.
SERIES IV. BOOKS contains little manuscript material, but includes correspondence, publicity, and reviews of his various books arranged chronologically by title.
SERIES V. MISCELLANEOUS, contains such items as clippings, diplomas, and passports.
The papers are the gift of Mrs. Catherine Embree Harris, 1964, 1967.
Biographical / Historical
Between 1917-1927, Edwin Rogers Embree served as secretary, director of the Division of Studies, and vice-president of the Rockefeller Foundation. Between 1928-1948, he was vice-president, director of the Division of Human Biology, and president of the Julius Rosenwald Fund.
CHRONOLOGY OF EDWIN ROGERS EMBREE
1883 Born 31 July at Osceola, Nebraska; youngest of seven children
1883 Father, Norris Jones Embree, Union Pacific Railroad Company, telegrapher
1883 Mother, Laura Ann (Fee) Embree, daughter of Rev. John Gregg Fee, abolitionist preacher and founder of Berea College (in Kentucky). Family later moved to Wyoming and then Kentucky where young Embree came under the influence of his grandfather, Rev. John Fee. Collection contains correspondence with his brother, William Dean Embree, '02, born in 1880 in Humbolt, Kansas.
1906 B.A. from Yale
1906-1907 Reporter, New York Sun
1907 16 July, Married Kate Scott; Embree had three children: John Fee; Edwina Rogers, Mrs. E. A. Devereux; Catherine Day, Mrs. A. L. Harris.
1907-1917 Member of administration at Yale:
1907-1909 Associate Editor, Yale Alumni Weekly; Met Clarence S. Day, Jr., '96.
1909-1911 Alumni Editor, Yale Alumni Weekly
1910 Organizer with Clarence S. Day, Jr., of Class Secretaries Bureau
1910-1917 Director of Class Secretaries Bureau
1911-1917 Alumni Registrar and Executive Assistant to Secretary, Yale University
1914-1917 Secretary, Bureau of Appointments
1914 M. A. in Philosophy from Yale
1917-1927 Association with Rockefeller Foundations:
1917-1923 Secretary, Rockefeller Foundations
1918 Trip to France as member of Rockefeller Tuberculosis Commission. Met Julius Rosenwald.
1924-1927 Director, Division of Studies, Rockefeller Foundation
1927 Vice-President, Rockefeller Foundation
1920 Trip to Europe
1921 Trip to China
1922 Trip to China
1923 Trip to Puerto Rico and Europe
1925-1926 Trip to Pacific
1927 Trip to Central America
1928-1948 Association with Julius Rosenwald Fund:
1928-1930 Vice-President and Director, Division Human Biology, Julius Rosenwald Fund
1930-1948 President, Julius Rosenwald Fund
1931 Publication - Brown America
1932 Death of Julius Rosenwald
1932 Trip to Samoa
1932 Publication - Prospecting for Heaven A New School for American Samoa
1933 Trip to Java
1934 Publication - Island India Goes To School Trip to Russia
1939 Publication - Indians of the Americas
1942 Publication - American Negroes
1943 Publication - Brown Americans
1944 Publication - Thirteen Against the Odds
1948-1949 Publication - Peoples of the Earth
1948-1949 President, Liberia Foundation. Associated with Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. Took trip to Liberia.
1949 Publication - "Timid Billions;" Investment in People; Death of Edward Stettinius
1949-1950 Consultant John Hay Whitney and Greenwood Foundations
1950 Death of Embree on February 21; death of his son, John F. Embree, and John's daughter, Clare, on December 22.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 167 instead of the originals.
African Americans; Anthropology; Charities; Charity organization; Education -- Aims and objectives; Endowment of research; Endowments; Humanitarianism; Social service; Africa; Asia; Europe -- Description and travel; Europe; Latin America; Soviet Union; United States -- Race relations; Chase, Harry Woodburn, 1883-1955; Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978; Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952; Day, Clarence, 1874-1935; Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers), 1883-1950; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952; Johnson, Charles Spurgeon, 1893-1956; Jordan, W. K. (Wilbur Kitchener), 1902-1980; Kilpatrick, William Heard, 1871-1965; Lohman, Joseph D. (Joseph Dean), 1910-1968; Raushenbush, Esther, 1898-1980; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970; Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960; Sparling, Edward James, 1896-; Taylor, Harold, 1914-1993; Julius Rosenwald Fund; Liberian Foundation, Inc; Rockefeller Foundation; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1906
- CORRESPONDENCE, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Note: Reel column indicates microfilm reel and frame number (i.e., reel:frame).
  - General Correspondence, 1912-1950; 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1-6, Reel 1:2, 1:57, 1:143, 1:231, 1:328, 1:474)
  - Adams, Maude, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1:520)
  - Bureau for Intercultural Education, 1948 September - 1948 February; 1949 March - 1950 February (Box 1, Folder 8-9, Reel 1:531)
  - Bureau for Intercultural Education—Testimonial Dinner, 1949 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1:670, 858)
  - Chase, Harry Woodburn (*)
    General note
    See: box 3, folder 29
  - Chicago Commission on Human Relations, 1948 September - 1949 October (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 2:2)
  - Chicago Industrial Health Association, 1949 March - 1950 February (Box 2, Folder 12, Reel 2:38)
  - Connecticut State Department of Education, 1949 March - November (Box 2, Folder 13, Reel 2:101)
  - Day, Clarence, 1926-1936 (Box 2, Folder 14-17, Reel 2:181, 2:250, 2:367, 2:418)
  - Day, Clarence—Subj. [PM, clippings] (Box 2, Folder 18, Reel 2:490)
  - Embree, William, 1927-1937 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2:550)
  - Embree Family [photographs], 1903-1950 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2:623)
  - Fisk University, 1948 August - 1950 February (Box 2, Folder 21, Reel 2:690)
  - Ford Foundation, 1948 December - 1949 April (Box 2, Folder 22, Reel 2:842)
  - Ickes, Harold L. (*)
    See: box 3, folders 32-33
  - Income Tax, 1938-1948 (Box 2, Folder 23, Reel 2:857)
  - Johnson, Charles S. (*)
    See: box 2, folder 21
  - Jordan, Wilbur K. (*)
    See: box 3, folder 31
  - Kilpatrick, William H.
    See: box 1, folders 8-9
  - Labor Foundation, 1949 March - September (Box 2, Folder 24, Reel 2:973)
  - Liberia Company, 1948 January - December (Box 3, Folder 25-26, Reel 3:2, 3:108)
  - Lohman, Joseph D.
    See: box 3, folder 28
  - McAllister, Frank (*)
  - Martin, Newell, 1935 February - 1936 February (Box 3, Folder 27, Reel 3:194)
  - National Committee on Segregation in the Nation's Capital, 1948 September - 1949 December (Box 3, Folder 28, Reel 3:223)
  - New York University, 1948 December - 1950 January (Box 3, Folder 29, Reel 3:256)
  - New York University School of Education, Center for Human Relations Studies (*)
  - Pearl, Raymond, 1928 March - 1939 May (Box 3, Folder 30, Reel 3:345)
  - Radcliffe College, 1948 October - 1950 February (Box 3, Folder 31, Reel 3:408)
  - Raushenbush, Esther (*)
    See: box 4, folders 36-38
  - Reuther, Walter
    See: box 2, folder 24
  - Roosevelt College, 1948 August - 1950 February (Box 3, Folder 32-33, Reel 3:498, 3:630)
  - Rosenwald Fund, 1927 November - 1928 May (Box 3, Folder 34, Reel 3:765)
  - Somoan Correspondence, 1932-1934 (Box 3, Folder 35, Reel 3:777)
  - Sarah Lawrence College, 1948 August - 1950 February (Box 4, Folder 36-38, Reel 3:795, 4:2, 4:121)
  - Sparling, Edward, J. (*)
  - Taylor, Harold (*)
  - Yale University and Yale Club, 1948 November - 1950 February (Box 4, Folder 39, Reel 4:261)
- FAMILY JOURNAL, Series II
  - Family Journal, 1918 (France) (Box 4, Folder 1, Reel 4:324)
  - Family Journal, 1920 (Europe) (Box 4, Folder 2, Reel 4:368)
  - Family Journal, 1921, 1922 (China) (Box 4, Folder 3-4, Reel 4:411, 4:433)
  - Family Journal, 1923 (Puerto Rico) (Box 4, Folder 5, Reel 4:453)
  - Family Journal, 1923 (Europe) (Box 4, Folder 6, Reel 4:458)
  - Family Journal, 1925-1926 (Pacific) (Box 4, Folder 7, Reel 4:476)
  - Family Journal, 1927 (Central America) (Box 4, Folder 8, Reel 4:519)
  - Family Journal, 1932 (Samoa) (Box 4, Folder 9, Reel 4:532)
  - Family Journal, 1933 (Java) (Box 4, Folder 10, Reel 4:617)
  - Family Journal, 1934 (Russia) (Box 5, Folder 11, Reel 5:2)
  - Family Journal, 1948-1949 (Liberia) (Box 5, Folder 12, Reel 5:63)
- ARTICLES, SPEECHES, TALKS, Series III
  - Embree Bibliography (Box 5, Folder 1, Reel 5:74)
  - Book Reviews by E. R. E. (Box 5, Folder 2, Reel 5:95)
  - Cultural Anthropology, 1922-1944 (Box 5, Folder 3-4, Reel 5:170, 5:432)
  - Cultural Anthropology—Notes on the Pacific (Box 5, Folder 5-7, Reel 5:611, 5:718, 5:793)
  - Education, 1928 April-1950 February (Box 6, Folder 8-13, Reel 6:2, 6:166, 6:247, 6:312, 6:414, 6:461)
  - Medicine and Nursing, 1923-1930 (Box 6, Folder 14-15, Reel 6:623, 6:659)
  - Miscellaneous, 1928-1949 (Box 6, Folder 16-17, Reel 6:703, 6:816)
  - Miscellaneous (undated) (Box 7, Folder 18, Reel 7:2)
  - Race Relations (American), 1929-1950 (Box 7, Folder 19, Reel 7:114)
  - Religion, 1926-1936 (Box 7, Folder 20, Reel 7:213)
  - Social Sciences (other), 1926-1950 (Box 7, Folder 21, Reel 7:276)
  - "Timid Billions" (drafts) (Box 7, Folder 22, Reel 7:321)
  - "Timid Billions" (reprints, reviews) (Box 7, Folder 23, Reel 7:431)
  - "Timid Billions" (correspondence), 1948 (Box 7, Folder 24, Reel 7:564)
  - "Timid Billions" correspondence, 1949 January - December (Box 7, Folder 25-28, Reel 7:579, 7:681, 7:754, 7:889)
- BOOKS, Series IV
  - Brown America - correspondence, publicity, 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 1, Reel 8:2)
  - Brown America - reviews (Box 8, Folder 2, Reel 8:90)
  - Brown America - correspondence, reviews, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 3, Reel 8:141)
  - Investment in People - correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 4, Reel 8:159)
  - Peoples of the Earth - correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 5, Reel 8:251)
  - Prospecting for Heaven - contributor's correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 6, Reel 8:442)
  - Prospecting for Heaven - correspondence, publicity, reviews, etc., 1932-1934 (Box 8, Folder 7, Reel 8:541)
  - Other books (Box 8, Folder 8, Reel 8:674)
  - Institute for Psychoanalysis and The World at the Crossroads (copies) (Box 8, Folder 9, Reel 8:753)
- MISCELLANEOUS, Series V
  - Diplomas, degrees, certificates (Box 9, Folder 1, Reel 9:2)
  - Clipping re: E. R. E., 1905-1950 (Box 9, Folder 2, Reel 9:9)
  - Obituary notices, tributes (Box 9, Folder 3, Reel 9:92)
  - Rosenwald Fund—Statements of Accounts; closing of fund, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 4-5, Reel 9:217, 9:267)
  - Passports (Box 9, Folder 6, Reel 9:274)
  - Miscellaneous print and near-print materials (Box 9, Folder 7, Reel 9:328)
  - Original drawings by Howard Greg for Indians of the Americas by E. R. E. (Box 9, Folder 8, Reel 9:478)
  - Biographical material (Box 9, Folder 9, Reel 9:482)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 10, Reel 9:523)